<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diogo Almeida | Roberto Petrosino</title>
    <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/diogo/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/diogo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Diogo Almeida</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2021} RP</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/diogo/avatar_hufb085fb5a3410f594ece1dde74f83012_16346_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Diogo Almeida</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/diogo/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphological decomposition: more than islands of regularity?</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A wealth of psycholinguistic evidence has shown that words, before being visually recognized, decompose into smaller units which seem to correspond to morphemes (Rastle et al., 2000, 2004). Such a procedure of &lt;em&gt;morphological decomposition&lt;/em&gt; seems to occur in words that are made of more than one morpheme, independently of whether they are semantically transparent (e.g., &lt;em&gt;driver&lt;/em&gt;, which means &amp;ldquo;someone who drives&amp;rdquo;) or not (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brother&lt;/em&gt;, which does not mean &amp;ldquo;someone who broths&amp;rdquo;). Decomposition, however, does not seem to occur in words that contain a root plus an additional, non-morphemic string (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brothel&lt;/em&gt;, where &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not an English suffix). Current models of visual word processing assume the &lt;em&gt;morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;, whereby decomposition obligatorily relies on &lt;em&gt;islands of regularity&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; namely, statistical orthographic regularities across letter strings, so that a string such as &lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt; is detected as a single morpho-orthographic unit, but &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not (Rastle &amp;amp; Davis 2008). As such, decomposition is also argued to occur at early stages of word processing and &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; contact with the lexicon &amp;mdash; namely, before semantic information is accessed, so that decomposition occurs regardless of semantic transparency. In my doctoral dissertation, I built on these findings and use the visual masked priming response to test the sensitivity of decomposition to any of the following higher-level linguistic properties (in addition to islands of regularities): phono-orthographic syllabification, whole-word frequency, phonological conditioning, and syntactic well-formedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYLLABIFICATION&lt;/strong&gt;. The hypothesis that decomposition goes through a mechanism of low-level syllabic chunking was first tested because it may explain why words that contain a root but not a second morpheme do not decompose (&lt;em&gt;brothel↛ broth-el&lt;/em&gt;; ‘brothel effect’; Rastle et al., 2004), but non-words that contain a root but not a second morpheme do (&lt;em&gt;flexire→flex-ire&lt;/em&gt;; ‘flexire effect’; Morris et al., 2011). One possibility is that the flexire effect results from the syllabic chunking operation (&lt;em&gt;flexire → FLEX.IRE → flex-ire&lt;/em&gt;; where the dot ‘.’ signals a loose syllabic boundary). The brothel effect would then be a consequence of averaging the priming response to words with a syllabic, non-affixal ending (&lt;em&gt;brothel → BROTH.EL → broth-el&lt;/em&gt;) together with the non-priming response to words with a non-syllabic, non-affixal ending (i.e., &lt;em&gt;against → AGAINST ↛ again-st&lt;/em&gt;). In our experiments, masked priming was elicited in two different orthographically related, but morphologically unrelated conditions: a syllabic condition, in which the prime word contained the corresponding target word, plus a syllabic unit (e.g., &lt;em&gt;ban.jo-BAN&lt;/em&gt;, where the dot “.” signals the syllabic boundary); and a non-syllabic condition, in which the prime word contained the corresponding target word, plus a consonantal unit (e.g., &lt;em&gt;starch-STAR&lt;/em&gt;, where the underlined string signals the extra consonantal unit). Results showed that both conditions did not elicit priming, thus suggesting that syllabification does not drive morphological decomposition (at least in the visual modality). These results potentially imply that decomposition is affected by the lexicality of the stimulus: in words, decomposition occurs only if they can be transparently broken down into morphemes; in non-words, decomposition occurs as long as they contain at least one morpheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOMINANCE&lt;/strong&gt;. The term ‘&lt;em&gt;dominance&lt;/em&gt;’ refers to the asymmetrical ratio between frequencies of the forms in the same nominal paradigm: for example, a word such as &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; is plural-dominant because the surface frequency of the plural form (&lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt;) is higher than the surface frequency of the singular form (&lt;em&gt;window&lt;/em&gt;); a word such as &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; is instead singular-dominant, because the surface frequency of the plural form (&lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt;) is lower than the surface frequency of the singular form (&lt;em&gt;world&lt;/em&gt;). Lexical decision studies have reported that plural-dominant plural forms are recognized faster than singular-dominant plural forms. The hypothesis that dominance potentially impinges on decomposition was tested to understand whether word frequency is accessed during decomposition, or, rather, at later stages of processing. Masked priming was elicited in two different morphological conditions: in the sgdom-sgdom condition, the pairs contained singular-dominant plural forms as both primes and targets (e.g., &lt;em&gt;worlds-HEAVENS&lt;/em&gt;); in the pldom-sgdom condition, the pairs contained a plural-dominant plural prime and a singular-dominant plural target (e.g., &lt;em&gt;windows-GODS&lt;/em&gt;). Results showed that priming arose in the sgdom-sgdom condition, but not in the pldom-sgdom condition, thus suggesting that dominance asymmetries (and therefore word frequency) impinge on decomposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYNTACTIC WELL-FORMEDNESS.&lt;/strong&gt; The term ‘syntactic well-formedness’ refers to the syntactic categories affixes may and may not attach to; for example, the affix &lt;em&gt;–(i)ble&lt;/em&gt; attaches to verbs, but not to nouns: e.g., &lt;em&gt;flex-ible&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;bliss-able&lt;/em&gt;. The hypothesis that decomposition is affected by violations of syntactic well-formedness restrictions was therefore tested to explore whether decomposition accesses syntactic properties of morphemes. In our experiments, the masked priming response was elicited for both syntactically well-formed and ill-formed prime stimuli &amp;ndash; e.g.,  &lt;em&gt;purity-PURE&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;skittity-SKIT&lt;/em&gt;. These results suggest that decomposition is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; affected by syntactic well-formedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, these results suggest that while not being affected by syntactic well-formedness, decomposition is indeed sensitive to whole-word lexicality and whole-word frequency. This clear-cut divide between properties that may and may not impinge on decomposition might be due to the fact that both syntactic processing (i.e., the process whereby syntactic categories and affixal restrictions are retrieved and checked) and semantic processing (i.e., the process whereby whole-word meaning is accessed) require at least two mechanisms to occur: (i) recombination of decomposed morphemes (along the lines of Taft 2004), and, eventually, (ii) access to compatible syntactic and semantic representations. Given that these are fairly complex, these representations indeed take more time to access fully, which, therefore, may not occur until after decomposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the face value, the fact that whole-word lexicality and frequency may impinge on early decomposition procedures is surprising. These two properties are generally considered to be accessed at late stages of processing and their potential implications onto decomposition seems logically contradictory, under the current theories of early decomposition: how can an early process be affected by properties that concern the whole stimulus and, as such, are accessed only at later stages? A model of early visual decomposition is proposed that is able to account for these findings without necessarily challenging the morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis. In this model, decomposition accesses whole-word lexicality and frequency through a multi-step mechanism that first generates multiple possible morpho-orthographic decomposition patterns of the visual stimulus and then evaluates them &lt;em&gt;in parallel&lt;/em&gt; in order to choose the optimal candidate for activation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation above has inspired a number of follow-up studies on morphological decomposition. Click on the links below for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Methodological questions&lt;/mark&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/primetime/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime masking in the auditory modality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Theoretical questions&lt;/mark&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/dominance_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dominance-driven morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selective morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phon_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phonology-driven morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological underspecification</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phono_underspecification/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phono_underspecification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since at least the 1970s, much research in theoretical phonology has been devoted to determining how speech sounds are represented in the human mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, Eulitz &amp;amp; Lahiri (2004) have demonstrated that EEG, and in particular the Mismatch Negativity (MMN) response, can be a powerful tool for investigating the featural specifications within the mental representations of speech sounds (Näätänen, 2001). Eulitz and Lahiri (2004) were the first to show that MMN amplitude is modulated by the amount of featural information stored in the long-term mental representation of speech sounds (asymmetrical MMNs; henceforth, aMMNs). Since that discovery, many studies have been carried out, that have systematically tested the aMMN response to speech sound across a wide variety of languages (a.o., Turkish: Lipski et al., 2007; English: Scharinger et al., 2012, 2016; Arabic, Russian: Schluter et al., 2017). At UConn, in collaboration with Jon Sprouse (UConn), Andrea Calabrese (UConn) and Diogo Almeida (NYUAD), I have begun to explore the foundations of the aMMN response, by asking to what extent it is language-specific, and to what extent it may be elicited in other complex cognitive domains. The ultimate goal of this line of research is to widen the set of cognitive (and, possibly, linguistically relevant) feature representations that we can investigate with the aMMN response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/&#34;&gt;first study&lt;/a&gt;, we elicited the MMN response to flatulence, which is assumed to be socially marked, and coughs and sniffs, which are both assumed to be socially unmarked. We chose these sounds for three reasons. First, they are relatively acoustically complex biological sounds, involving complex frequency spectra, similar to speech sounds. Second, social markedness is likely an abstract representation that must be learned, as it can vary across cultures, similar to the abstract representation of speech sounds, which can vary across languages. Finally, markedness is a theoretical primitive in linguistics (a.o., Jakobson &amp;amp; Halle, 1956; Chomsky &amp;amp; Halle, 1968; Kiparsky, 1982; Prince &amp;amp; Smolensky, 1993/2004; Calabrese, 2005), though it is relatively understudied in speech perception. Social markedness, though external to language, may therefore be abstractly similar to linguistic markedness. Therefore, the stimuli used arguably provided a minimal contrast with linguistic aMMNs, differing primarily in the domain of cognition. Our analyses showed that non-linguistic biological sounds trigger asymmetrical MMN responses in a way that tracks the social categorization of those sounds as socially-marked/unacceptable (such as flatulence) and socially-unmarked/acceptable (such as coughs and sniffs), but does not track the physical properties of the sounds (in which coughs and sniffs are most distinct, with flatulence in between). These results suggest that aMMNs may not be specific to language, and also that social cognition categories appear to impinge on early stages of auditory processing in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings open the door to several avenues of research spanning diverse branches of the cognitive sciences. For example, these findings may lead to follow-up studies exploring the extent to which linguistic aMMNs are modulated by other representational properties beyond featural specification – for example, phonological markedness and phonological contrastiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetrical Mismatch Negativities to Socially-Marked Biological Sounds</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study explores to what extent social cognition impacts early auditory processing. We measured the Mismatch Negativity (MMN) response to three non-linguistic biological sounds (flatulence, coughs and sniffs) that differ in terms of social markedness: flatulence is socially marked, while coughs and sniffs are not. We found that the MMN to the pairing flatulence/cough is larger when flatulence is the oddball than when cough is the oddball – an asymmetrical MMN. We found no evidence of an asymmetrical MMN for the pairing cough/sniff. Crucially, this pattern tracks the social-markedness properties of these stimuli, but does not track their physical properties. The MMN response has long been used for research in language and music; these results suggest that it may also be used for research in social cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lexical selectivity in visual morphological decomposition</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some preliminary results reported in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/uploads/Petrosino_Dissertation2020.pdf&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, priming effects are shown to arise for specific affixes: i.e., &lt;em&gt;-able&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ful&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;im-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ity&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ment&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ness&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-s&lt;/em&gt;; but not for others: &lt;em&gt;dis-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;in-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-er&lt;/em&gt;. These unexpected results suggest a &lt;em&gt;lexically selective&lt;/em&gt; procedure of visual morphological decomposition, which is contingent on some property (let it be purely orthographical or, rather, more linguistically abstract) associated to the affix being involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a claim, if true, would challenge all existing theories of early decomposition, in which &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; morphemes are predicted to  systematically undergo decomposition (for a review, Rastle &amp;amp; Davis 2008). At this stage of research, there seems to be no theoretically-relevant, testable hypothesis behind the distinction between decomposable and non-decomposable morphemes. It is also important to acknowledge that the experiments reported in the dissertation were run online, which have brought about technical issues during data collection (prime duration fluctuations, suboptimal RT reliability) and, as a result, a high amount of noise in the data. The lack of priming for some affixes might have therefore arisen because of technical and methodological issues, rather than theoretically interesting ones. As preliminary step towards further understanding the results reported in the dissertation, we expect to re-run the same experiments in an in-lab environment, which guarantees more control over sources of noise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prime masking in the auditory modality</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most psycholinguistic research on morphological decomposition has been conducted in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/&#34;&gt;visual modality&lt;/a&gt;. The main reason for this is that our current behavioral methodologies seem unable to investigate auditory decomposition at the subliminal level of processing. Since auditory stimuli typically unfold over time, the masking procedure of auditory prime stimuli is particularly harder to implement. In recent years, however, the pioneering study by Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005) has provided an interesting way to implement prime masking in auditory priming. This technique resembles the typical prime-target sound stream, but features the following specifics (see the figure below). All primes are first intensity-attenuated and then time-compressed, so that their original duration was reduced to usually between 35% and 40% of their original duration. Randomly selected, attenuated, and time-compressed primes are also time-reversed to create auditory masks. Each time-compressed prime is preceded by one mask and followed by four other different masks; the target word (at normal speech rate and volume) is imposed over the sequence of masks and prime so that the onset of the target coincided with the offset of the prime.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-schematic-description-of-a-typical-trial-in-kouider--dupoux-2005s-auditory-masked-priming-paradigm-the-attenuated-and-time-compressed-prime-is-immediately-preceded-and-followed-by-attenuated-time-compressed-and-time-reversed-masks-as-indicated-by-the-label-_ksam_-ie-the-word-_mask_-in-reverse-the-target-is-played-at-normal-speech-rate-and-is-not-attenuated-it-immediately-follows-the-prime-ie-its-onset-coincides-with-the-offset-of-the-prime-and-is-superimposed-on-the-rightward-mask-stream&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Schematic description of a typical trial in Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005)&amp;#39;s auditory masked priming paradigm. The attenuated and time-compressed prime is immediately preceded and followed by attenuated, time-compressed, and time-reversed masks (as indicated by the label _ksam_, i.e. the word &amp;#39;_mask_&amp;#39; in reverse). The target is played at normal speech rate and is not attenuated; it immediately follows the prime (i.e., its onset coincides with the offset of the prime) and is superimposed on the rightward mask stream.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_db04109d229b6091a8213cc636dc8d24.jpg 400w,
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_d0f826acaf000396cf125de3c2328d3d.jpg 760w,
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_db04109d229b6091a8213cc636dc8d24.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Schematic description of a typical trial in Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005)&amp;rsquo;s auditory masked priming paradigm. The attenuated and time-compressed prime is immediately preceded and followed by attenuated, time-compressed, and time-reversed masks (as indicated by the label &lt;em&gt;ksam&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. the word &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;mask&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; in reverse). The target is played at normal speech rate and is not attenuated; it immediately follows the prime (i.e., its onset coincides with the offset of the prime) and is superimposed on the rightward mask stream.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants usually report hearing a clear word (i.e., the target word sound) surrounded by unintelligible babble. As an illustrative example, play the audio file right below: the target word &lt;em&gt;SHARP&lt;/em&gt; is preceded by what looks like babble, in which an attenuated, time-compressed prime was imposed over a stream of attenuated, time-compressed and time-reversed words.&lt;/p&gt;






  








&lt;audio controls &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;audMskPr_example.mp3&#34; type=&#34;audio/mpeg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While promising, the design described above however proved to suffer from a number of methodological issues, as preliminary tests have shown. The issues seem to be connected to the interplay between the time-compression rate and the phonological length of the prime stimuli, which have a substantial impact on the subliminal intelligibility of the prime &amp;ndash; and, ultimately, to priming elicitation. A full-length study is being conducted that explores the interdependence of compression duration, the linguistic/acoustic factors just mentioned, and priming effects, with the ultimate goal of defining the minimum compressed duration at which priming can be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
