<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Roberto Petrosino</title>
    <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/robpetro/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/robpetro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Roberto Petrosino</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2021} RP</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/robpetro/avatar_hu7c5d4bd1f9f45866b954069ab288cd29_132564_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.JPG</url>
      <title>Roberto Petrosino</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/authors/robpetro/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphological decomposition: more than islands of regularity?</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A wealth of psycholinguistic evidence has shown that words, before being visually recognized, decompose into smaller units which seem to correspond to morphemes (Rastle et al., 2000, 2004). Such a procedure of &lt;em&gt;morphological decomposition&lt;/em&gt; seems to occur in words that are made of more than one morpheme, independently of whether they are semantically transparent (e.g., &lt;em&gt;driver&lt;/em&gt;, which means &amp;ldquo;someone who drives&amp;rdquo;) or not (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brother&lt;/em&gt;, which does not mean &amp;ldquo;someone who broths&amp;rdquo;). Decomposition, however, does not seem to occur in words that contain a root plus an additional, non-morphemic string (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brothel&lt;/em&gt;, where &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not an English suffix). Current models of visual word processing assume the &lt;em&gt;morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;, whereby decomposition obligatorily relies on &lt;em&gt;islands of regularity&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; namely, statistical orthographic regularities across letter strings, so that a string such as &lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt; is detected as a single morpho-orthographic unit, but &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not (Rastle &amp;amp; Davis 2008). As such, decomposition is also argued to occur at early stages of word processing and &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; contact with the lexicon &amp;mdash; namely, before semantic information is accessed, so that decomposition occurs regardless of semantic transparency. In my doctoral dissertation, I built on these findings and use the visual masked priming response to test the sensitivity of decomposition to any of the following higher-level linguistic properties (in addition to islands of regularities): phono-orthographic syllabification, whole-word frequency, phonological conditioning, and syntactic well-formedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYLLABIFICATION&lt;/strong&gt;. The hypothesis that decomposition goes through a mechanism of low-level syllabic chunking was first tested because it may explain why words that contain a root but not a second morpheme do not decompose (&lt;em&gt;brothel↛ broth-el&lt;/em&gt;; ‘brothel effect’; Rastle et al., 2004), but non-words that contain a root but not a second morpheme do (&lt;em&gt;flexire→flex-ire&lt;/em&gt;; ‘flexire effect’; Morris et al., 2011). One possibility is that the flexire effect results from the syllabic chunking operation (&lt;em&gt;flexire → FLEX.IRE → flex-ire&lt;/em&gt;; where the dot ‘.’ signals a loose syllabic boundary). The brothel effect would then be a consequence of averaging the priming response to words with a syllabic, non-affixal ending (&lt;em&gt;brothel → BROTH.EL → broth-el&lt;/em&gt;) together with the non-priming response to words with a non-syllabic, non-affixal ending (i.e., &lt;em&gt;against → AGAINST ↛ again-st&lt;/em&gt;). In our experiments, masked priming was elicited in two different orthographically related, but morphologically unrelated conditions: a syllabic condition, in which the prime word contained the corresponding target word, plus a syllabic unit (e.g., &lt;em&gt;ban.jo-BAN&lt;/em&gt;, where the dot “.” signals the syllabic boundary); and a non-syllabic condition, in which the prime word contained the corresponding target word, plus a consonantal unit (e.g., &lt;em&gt;starch-STAR&lt;/em&gt;, where the underlined string signals the extra consonantal unit). Results showed that both conditions did not elicit priming, thus suggesting that syllabification does not drive morphological decomposition (at least in the visual modality). These results potentially imply that decomposition is affected by the lexicality of the stimulus: in words, decomposition occurs only if they can be transparently broken down into morphemes; in non-words, decomposition occurs as long as they contain at least one morpheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOMINANCE&lt;/strong&gt;. The term ‘&lt;em&gt;dominance&lt;/em&gt;’ refers to the asymmetrical ratio between frequencies of the forms in the same nominal paradigm: for example, a word such as &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; is plural-dominant because the surface frequency of the plural form (&lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt;) is higher than the surface frequency of the singular form (&lt;em&gt;window&lt;/em&gt;); a word such as &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; is instead singular-dominant, because the surface frequency of the plural form (&lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt;) is lower than the surface frequency of the singular form (&lt;em&gt;world&lt;/em&gt;). Lexical decision studies have reported that plural-dominant plural forms are recognized faster than singular-dominant plural forms. The hypothesis that dominance potentially impinges on decomposition was tested to understand whether word frequency is accessed during decomposition, or, rather, at later stages of processing. Masked priming was elicited in two different morphological conditions: in the sgdom-sgdom condition, the pairs contained singular-dominant plural forms as both primes and targets (e.g., &lt;em&gt;worlds-HEAVENS&lt;/em&gt;); in the pldom-sgdom condition, the pairs contained a plural-dominant plural prime and a singular-dominant plural target (e.g., &lt;em&gt;windows-GODS&lt;/em&gt;). Results showed that priming arose in the sgdom-sgdom condition, but not in the pldom-sgdom condition, thus suggesting that dominance asymmetries (and therefore word frequency) impinge on decomposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYNTACTIC WELL-FORMEDNESS.&lt;/strong&gt; The term ‘syntactic well-formedness’ refers to the syntactic categories affixes may and may not attach to; for example, the affix &lt;em&gt;–(i)ble&lt;/em&gt; attaches to verbs, but not to nouns: e.g., &lt;em&gt;flex-ible&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;bliss-able&lt;/em&gt;. The hypothesis that decomposition is affected by violations of syntactic well-formedness restrictions was therefore tested to explore whether decomposition accesses syntactic properties of morphemes. In our experiments, the masked priming response was elicited for both syntactically well-formed and ill-formed prime stimuli &amp;ndash; e.g.,  &lt;em&gt;purity-PURE&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;skittity-SKIT&lt;/em&gt;. These results suggest that decomposition is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; affected by syntactic well-formedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, these results suggest that while not being affected by syntactic well-formedness, decomposition is indeed sensitive to whole-word lexicality and whole-word frequency. This clear-cut divide between properties that may and may not impinge on decomposition might be due to the fact that both syntactic processing (i.e., the process whereby syntactic categories and affixal restrictions are retrieved and checked) and semantic processing (i.e., the process whereby whole-word meaning is accessed) require at least two mechanisms to occur: (i) recombination of decomposed morphemes (along the lines of Taft 2004), and, eventually, (ii) access to compatible syntactic and semantic representations. Given that these are fairly complex, these representations indeed take more time to access fully, which, therefore, may not occur until after decomposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the face value, the fact that whole-word lexicality and frequency may impinge on early decomposition procedures is surprising. These two properties are generally considered to be accessed at late stages of processing and their potential implications onto decomposition seems logically contradictory, under the current theories of early decomposition: how can an early process be affected by properties that concern the whole stimulus and, as such, are accessed only at later stages? A model of early visual decomposition is proposed that is able to account for these findings without necessarily challenging the morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis. In this model, decomposition accesses whole-word lexicality and frequency through a multi-step mechanism that first generates multiple possible morpho-orthographic decomposition patterns of the visual stimulus and then evaluates them &lt;em&gt;in parallel&lt;/em&gt; in order to choose the optimal candidate for activation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation above has inspired a number of follow-up studies on morphological decomposition. Click on the links below for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Methodological questions&lt;/mark&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/primetime/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime masking in the auditory modality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Theoretical questions&lt;/mark&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/dominance_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dominance-driven morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selective morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phon_decomposition/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phonology-driven morphological decomposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological underspecification</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phono_underspecification/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phono_underspecification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since at least the 1970s, much research in theoretical phonology has been devoted to determining how speech sounds are represented in the human mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, Eulitz &amp;amp; Lahiri (2004) have demonstrated that EEG, and in particular the Mismatch Negativity (MMN) response, can be a powerful tool for investigating the featural specifications within the mental representations of speech sounds (Näätänen, 2001). Eulitz and Lahiri (2004) were the first to show that MMN amplitude is modulated by the amount of featural information stored in the long-term mental representation of speech sounds (asymmetrical MMNs; henceforth, aMMNs). Since that discovery, many studies have been carried out, that have systematically tested the aMMN response to speech sound across a wide variety of languages (a.o., Turkish: Lipski et al., 2007; English: Scharinger et al., 2012, 2016; Arabic, Russian: Schluter et al., 2017). At UConn, in collaboration with Jon Sprouse (UConn), Andrea Calabrese (UConn) and Diogo Almeida (NYUAD), I have begun to explore the foundations of the aMMN response, by asking to what extent it is language-specific, and to what extent it may be elicited in other complex cognitive domains. The ultimate goal of this line of research is to widen the set of cognitive (and, possibly, linguistically relevant) feature representations that we can investigate with the aMMN response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/&#34;&gt;first study&lt;/a&gt;, we elicited the MMN response to flatulence, which is assumed to be socially marked, and coughs and sniffs, which are both assumed to be socially unmarked. We chose these sounds for three reasons. First, they are relatively acoustically complex biological sounds, involving complex frequency spectra, similar to speech sounds. Second, social markedness is likely an abstract representation that must be learned, as it can vary across cultures, similar to the abstract representation of speech sounds, which can vary across languages. Finally, markedness is a theoretical primitive in linguistics (a.o., Jakobson &amp;amp; Halle, 1956; Chomsky &amp;amp; Halle, 1968; Kiparsky, 1982; Prince &amp;amp; Smolensky, 1993/2004; Calabrese, 2005), though it is relatively understudied in speech perception. Social markedness, though external to language, may therefore be abstractly similar to linguistic markedness. Therefore, the stimuli used arguably provided a minimal contrast with linguistic aMMNs, differing primarily in the domain of cognition. Our analyses showed that non-linguistic biological sounds trigger asymmetrical MMN responses in a way that tracks the social categorization of those sounds as socially-marked/unacceptable (such as flatulence) and socially-unmarked/acceptable (such as coughs and sniffs), but does not track the physical properties of the sounds (in which coughs and sniffs are most distinct, with flatulence in between). These results suggest that aMMNs may not be specific to language, and also that social cognition categories appear to impinge on early stages of auditory processing in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings open the door to several avenues of research spanning diverse branches of the cognitive sciences. For example, these findings may lead to follow-up studies exploring the extent to which linguistic aMMNs are modulated by other representational properties beyond featural specification – for example, phonological markedness and phonological contrastiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EEG/MEG response comparability</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/eeg_meg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/eeg_meg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few decades, a bulk of psycholinguistic evidence have shown that words decompose in morphemes when they are recognized (&lt;em&gt;morphological decomposition&lt;/em&gt;). A series of magnetoencephalographic (MEG) studies have recently suggested that the brain response to morphological properties originates from a region of the inferior temporal cortex known as `Visual Word Fom Area&#39; (VWFA; Cohen et al. 2000, Cohen et al. 2002) and peaks at about 150 ms post stimulus onset (the M170 component). This area of the brain has been shown to be sensitive to the morpho-orthographic statistical regularities at play during the early stages of the processing of non-affixed (heteronyms: e.g.,  &lt;em&gt;wind&lt;/em&gt;; Solomyak &amp;amp; Marantz 2009), affixed (e.g., bi-morphemic words involving free and bound stems: e.g. &lt;em&gt;taxable, tolerable&lt;/em&gt;; Solomyak &amp;amp; Marantz 2010), and pseudo-affixed (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brother&lt;/em&gt;; Lewis et al. 2011) words, but not to semantic properties, which seem to be indexed by a response in the superior temporal and Silvyan Fissure region peaking at about 350 ms (the M350 component; Pylkännen &amp;amp; Marantz 2003). These studies have developed a novel approach to MEG data analysis, which is based on the correlational data analysis approach pioneered by Hauk et al. (2006) for ERP sensor-space data analysis. While traditional data analysis pipelines group together stimuli sharing some properties in different conditions and compare them to one another, this new approach correlates a given variable (e.g., orthographic transitional probability) of &lt;em&gt;each stimulus&lt;/em&gt; with the brain response arising at a given time window. This kind of technique is particularly beneficial for investigations on morphological phenomena, which often consists of a small number of stimuli, which would be impossible to control for all the necessary variables. Unfortunately, not many morphologists that do not have access to highly expensive MEG machines, as there are, indeed, only a few available worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project explores the possibility of applying the MEG correlational technique just mentioned to high-density EEG data as a way to provide a reliable and a cost-effective methodology for morphologists interested in conducting electrophysiological research. So far, we have collected high-density EEG data for an identical replication of Lewis et al. (2011). In this study, the M170 response to both transparent (e.g., &lt;em&gt;driver&lt;/em&gt;) and opaque (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brother&lt;/em&gt;) words is shown to correlate with the morpho-orthographic transitional probability between pseudo-stem (&lt;em&gt;broth&lt;/em&gt;) and pseudo-affix (&lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt;), which supports the morpho-orthographic nature of early visual decomposition. We are now in the process of defining the EEG-adapted pipeline and comparing the two sets of results to one another. The hope is to obtain an agreed-on pipeline for correlational data analysis, which may guarantee comparability across types of signal (i.e., MEG vs. EEG) and boost electrophysiological research in morphology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetrical Mismatch Negativities to Socially-Marked Biological Sounds</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/mmns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study explores to what extent social cognition impacts early auditory processing. We measured the Mismatch Negativity (MMN) response to three non-linguistic biological sounds (flatulence, coughs and sniffs) that differ in terms of social markedness: flatulence is socially marked, while coughs and sniffs are not. We found that the MMN to the pairing flatulence/cough is larger when flatulence is the oddball than when cough is the oddball – an asymmetrical MMN. We found no evidence of an asymmetrical MMN for the pairing cough/sniff. Crucially, this pattern tracks the social-markedness properties of these stimuli, but does not track their physical properties. The MMN response has long been used for research in language and music; these results suggest that it may also be used for research in social cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Allomorphy: when, how, why</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/allomorphy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/allomorphy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent year, much effort in theoretical linguistics has devoted to defining the grammatical restrictions governing morphological alternations, in which the exponence of an element &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; depends on the context in which &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; occurs. While the context may be of different nature &amp;ndash; i.e., morpho-syntactic, phonological, and/or morpho-phonological &amp;ndash; my research focuses primarily on identifying the grammatical conditions triggering morpho-syntactically conditioned and morpho-phonologically conditions alternations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In morpho-syntactically conditioned alternations, the context is purely morpho-syntactic. For example, the English alternation go/went is usually posited as morpho-syntactically-conditioned, as consisting of a suppletive alternation exclusively triggered by a specific morpho-syntactic trigger (in our example, past tense). One question that researchers have been interested in is whether there are locality constraints acting upon allomorphy and what the relevant constraints are (Embick 2010; Bobaljik 2012; Merchant 2015; Moskal 2015; Moskal &amp;amp; Smith 2016). A strong hypothesis defended in Embick (2010) claims that, the trigger and the target of allomorphy must be linearly adjacent to each other (Linear Adjacency Hypothesis; LAH). Merchant (2015) has however pointed out that Greek root-allomorphy presents a counterexample to LAH, and proposes that vocabulary items are rather sensitive to &lt;em&gt;spans&lt;/em&gt; (i.e., larger portions of morpho-syntactic structures; Span Adjacency Hypothesis, SAH). &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/uploads/ChristopoulosPetrosino_GreekSpans_WCCFL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Christopoulos &amp;amp; Petrosino (2017)&lt;/a&gt; take issue with Merchant&amp;rsquo;s claim and propose a revisited analysis of Greek verbal morphology that seems to further support the LAH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morpho-phonologically conditioned alternations involve a phonological change triggered by morpho-syntactic and/or morpho-phonological trigger. Traditionally, these alternations are accounted for via application of morpho-phonological rules (i.e., the so-called readjustment rules). By the way of mixing phonological and morphological alphabets, these operations though make unfalsifiable predictions; as a consequence, a recent trend in the field has been to get rid of them as a whole (Bermùdez-Otero 2012, Haugen &amp;amp; Siddiqi 2013). In Petrosino (in prep.; available upon request), I discuss the morpho-phonologically conditioned allomorphy of the definite determiner in Neapolitan (southern Italian dialect) and argue for an account which is effortlessly able to explain the patterns as framed into language-wide generalizations governed by morpho-phonologically sensitive operations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dominance-driven morphological decomposition</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/dominance_decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/dominance_decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;dominance&lt;/em&gt; refers to the relative frequency of a given derived or inflected word form with respect to its stem word form. For example, a plural form such as &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; is labeled as &lt;strong&gt;singular-dominant&lt;/strong&gt; because the inflected form &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; is less frequent than the stem form &lt;em&gt;world&lt;/em&gt;; conversely, a plural form such as &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; is labeled as &lt;strong&gt;plural-dominant&lt;/strong&gt; because the inflected form &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; is more frequent than the stem form &lt;em&gt;window&lt;/em&gt;. In traditional lexical decision tasks, plural-dominant forms ( &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; ) has been shown to be recognized faster than singular-dominant forms ( &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; ). In light of these results, Baayen et al. (1997) made a strong claim in support of Schreuder &amp;amp; Baayen (1995)&amp;rsquo;s dual-route &lt;strong&gt;race model&lt;/strong&gt;, in which word recognition goes through both a parsing (decomposition) route and a storage (whole-form search) route. The route that reaches the recognition point first &amp;ldquo;wins&amp;rdquo; the race, in the sense that it is responsible for recognition. In singular-dominant plural forms ( &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; ), the whole form is low-frequency, so the storage route takes time to search for it in the lexicon; this allows the form to go through decomposition and therefore be recognized in the parsing route. In plural-dominant plural forms ( &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; ), the whole form is high-frequency, so the storage route recognizes it faster than the parsing route would; hence, the fast response to &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; is due to activation of the whole-form unit in the storage route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that in the race model, the two routes run independently of one another. This means that the decomposition procedures in the parsing route and the whole-word lexical search in the storage route occur regardless of which route ends up being responsible for recognition. We tested this hypothesis in a visual masked priming experiment, in which we elicited the priming response to (i) singular-dominant plural prime forms (sgdom-sgdom condition; e.g., &lt;em&gt;worlds-HEAVENS&lt;/em&gt;); and (ii) plural-dominant plural forms (pldom-sgdom condition; e.g., &lt;em&gt;windows-GODS&lt;/em&gt;). Results showed that priming arose in the sgdom-sgdom condition, but not in the pldom-sgdom condition, thus suggesting that dominance asymmetries (and therefore word frequency) impinge on decomposition. This seems to suggest a model of decomposition in which activation of morpho-orthographic units at early stages of processing may be affected by their &lt;em&gt;resting activation level&lt;/em&gt;, which is generally assumed to correlate with their frequency. In such a model, at early stages both the whole-form and stem-form units compete with one another for activation. Competition is solve through the mechanism of &lt;em&gt;lateral inhibition&lt;/em&gt;, in which a unit with a higher resting activation level activates faster and therefore inhibits the other competing, compatible units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model just outlined predicts the priming response to be systematically affected by dominance asymmetries between the affixed and the stem forms, regardless of the affix being used and of the priming type being elicited (i.e., root/affix priming). A series of experiments are currently being designed and carried out to test this prediction, in which the masked priming response is elicited to stem- and affixed-dominant words sharing the same affix.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lexical selectivity in visual morphological decomposition</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/sel_decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some preliminary results reported in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/uploads/Petrosino_Dissertation2020.pdf&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, priming effects are shown to arise for specific affixes: i.e., &lt;em&gt;-able&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ful&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;im-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ity&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ment&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-ness&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-s&lt;/em&gt;; but not for others: &lt;em&gt;dis-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;in-&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;-er&lt;/em&gt;. These unexpected results suggest a &lt;em&gt;lexically selective&lt;/em&gt; procedure of visual morphological decomposition, which is contingent on some property (let it be purely orthographical or, rather, more linguistically abstract) associated to the affix being involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a claim, if true, would challenge all existing theories of early decomposition, in which &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; morphemes are predicted to  systematically undergo decomposition (for a review, Rastle &amp;amp; Davis 2008). At this stage of research, there seems to be no theoretically-relevant, testable hypothesis behind the distinction between decomposable and non-decomposable morphemes. It is also important to acknowledge that the experiments reported in the dissertation were run online, which have brought about technical issues during data collection (prime duration fluctuations, suboptimal RT reliability) and, as a result, a high amount of noise in the data. The lack of priming for some affixes might have therefore arisen because of technical and methodological issues, rather than theoretically interesting ones. As preliminary step towards further understanding the results reported in the dissertation, we expect to re-run the same experiments in an in-lab environment, which guarantees more control over sources of noise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonology-driven decomposition</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phon_decomposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/phon_decomposition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project asks whether decomposition is affected by phonologically-conditioned morphological alternations, in which the alternants realize the same value of a given morpho-syntactic feature and can be accounted for by assuming language-wide, regular phonological operations triggered by the surrounding phonological context. For example, the realization of this prefix &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; alternates between [im] and [in], on whether the following root-initial phonological segment is a labial consonant or not: &lt;em&gt;i[n]tollerable&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;i[m]possible&lt;/em&gt;. These alternations are generally dealt with as resulting from general phonological processes (&lt;em&gt;rules&lt;/em&gt; and/or &lt;em&gt;constraints&lt;/em&gt;) operating on a single underlying form. In the example above, it is generally assumed that the underlying form of the prefix &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; is [in], in which the nasal becomes [m] via an assimilation process triggered in front of labial sounds. One way to test this is to elicit the priming response to word pairs in which each alternant occurs either as a prime or as a target: e.g., &lt;em&gt;intollerable-IMPOSSIBLE&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;impossible-INTOLLERABLE&lt;/em&gt;. In doing this, we ask two different, but related questions. The first question asks whether decomposition is able to detect the morpho-phonological relationship between alternating realizations of the same morpheme. The second question asked whether decomposition is able to detect the morpho-phonological asymmetry between phonologically-conditioned alternants, whereby one alternant (i.e., [im] phonologically derives from the other (i.e., [in]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternations such as the one exemplified above represent the simplex case of phonological conditioning in morphology, as they involve exactly &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; phonological operation. If the priming response were found to be sensitive to such simplex cases, it may be probed as a way to test competing phonological accounts for more complex phonologically-conditioned alternations, in which more than one phonological operation interact with one another. Derivational theories assume that phonological processes are ordered serially so that the surface form results from multiple, intermediate stages in which the underlying form undergoes rule in a fixed order (Chomsky &amp;amp; Halle 1968). Representational theories assume, instead, that phonological processes all occur in parallel and compete with one another for output selection ( &lt;em&gt;Optimality Theory&lt;/em&gt;: Prince &amp;amp; Smolensky 2008). These two theories of phonology therefore make different predictions with respect to the number of grammatical operations involved in the computation, which have been argued to affect processing time and therefore response times ( &lt;em&gt;derivational theory of complexity&lt;/em&gt;, DTC; Miller &amp;amp; Chomsky1963, Phillips 1996). On one hand, derivational theories predict that the parser analyzes the stimulus by applying the rules &amp;ldquo;in reverse&amp;rdquo; to go back to the underlying representation (which is assumed to be the long-term representation). As such, decomposition procedures are predicted to take more time depending on the the number of rules to undo to get to the corresponding long-term representation. On the other hand, representational theories predict that multiple phonological processes are all evaluated in parallel. Therefore, decomposition procedures are predicted to be unaffected by the number of processes involved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prime masking in the auditory modality</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/audmskpriming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most psycholinguistic research on morphological decomposition has been conducted in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/projects/decomposition/&#34;&gt;visual modality&lt;/a&gt;. The main reason for this is that our current behavioral methodologies seem unable to investigate auditory decomposition at the subliminal level of processing. Since auditory stimuli typically unfold over time, the masking procedure of auditory prime stimuli is particularly harder to implement. In recent years, however, the pioneering study by Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005) has provided an interesting way to implement prime masking in auditory priming. This technique resembles the typical prime-target sound stream, but features the following specifics (see the figure below). All primes are first intensity-attenuated and then time-compressed, so that their original duration was reduced to usually between 35% and 40% of their original duration. Randomly selected, attenuated, and time-compressed primes are also time-reversed to create auditory masks. Each time-compressed prime is preceded by one mask and followed by four other different masks; the target word (at normal speech rate and volume) is imposed over the sequence of masks and prime so that the onset of the target coincided with the offset of the prime.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-schematic-description-of-a-typical-trial-in-kouider--dupoux-2005s-auditory-masked-priming-paradigm-the-attenuated-and-time-compressed-prime-is-immediately-preceded-and-followed-by-attenuated-time-compressed-and-time-reversed-masks-as-indicated-by-the-label-_ksam_-ie-the-word-_mask_-in-reverse-the-target-is-played-at-normal-speech-rate-and-is-not-attenuated-it-immediately-follows-the-prime-ie-its-onset-coincides-with-the-offset-of-the-prime-and-is-superimposed-on-the-rightward-mask-stream&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Schematic description of a typical trial in Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005)&amp;#39;s auditory masked priming paradigm. The attenuated and time-compressed prime is immediately preceded and followed by attenuated, time-compressed, and time-reversed masks (as indicated by the label _ksam_, i.e. the word &amp;#39;_mask_&amp;#39; in reverse). The target is played at normal speech rate and is not attenuated; it immediately follows the prime (i.e., its onset coincides with the offset of the prime) and is superimposed on the rightward mask stream.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_db04109d229b6091a8213cc636dc8d24.jpg 400w,
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_d0f826acaf000396cf125de3c2328d3d.jpg 760w,
               /media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://robpetrosino.github.io/media/audMskPr_trial_hua5a477298e30fac8849d37ad700df132_56055_db04109d229b6091a8213cc636dc8d24.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Schematic description of a typical trial in Kouider &amp;amp; Dupoux (2005)&amp;rsquo;s auditory masked priming paradigm. The attenuated and time-compressed prime is immediately preceded and followed by attenuated, time-compressed, and time-reversed masks (as indicated by the label &lt;em&gt;ksam&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. the word &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;mask&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; in reverse). The target is played at normal speech rate and is not attenuated; it immediately follows the prime (i.e., its onset coincides with the offset of the prime) and is superimposed on the rightward mask stream.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants usually report hearing a clear word (i.e., the target word sound) surrounded by unintelligible babble. As an illustrative example, play the audio file right below: the target word &lt;em&gt;SHARP&lt;/em&gt; is preceded by what looks like babble, in which an attenuated, time-compressed prime was imposed over a stream of attenuated, time-compressed and time-reversed words.&lt;/p&gt;






  








&lt;audio controls &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;audMskPr_example.mp3&#34; type=&#34;audio/mpeg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While promising, the design described above however proved to suffer from a number of methodological issues, as preliminary tests have shown. The issues seem to be connected to the interplay between the time-compression rate and the phonological length of the prime stimuli, which have a substantial impact on the subliminal intelligibility of the prime &amp;ndash; and, ultimately, to priming elicitation. A full-length study is being conducted that explores the interdependence of compression duration, the linguistic/acoustic factors just mentioned, and priming effects, with the ultimate goal of defining the minimum compressed duration at which priming can be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More than Islands of Regularity: An Investigation of the Sensitivity of Morphological Decomposition to Higher-level Linguistic Properties</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/dissertation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A wealth of psycholinguistic evidence has shown that words, before being visually recognized, decompose into smaller units which seem to correspond to morphemes (Rastle et al. 2000, Rastle et al. 2004). Such a procedure of &lt;em&gt;morphological decomposition&lt;/em&gt; seems to occur in words that are made of more than one morpheme, independently of whether they are semantically transparent (e.g., &lt;em&gt;driver&lt;/em&gt;, which means &amp;lsquo;someone who drives&amp;rsquo;) or not (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brother&lt;/em&gt;, which does not mean &amp;lsquo;someone who broths&amp;rsquo;). Decomposition, however, does not seem to occur in words that contain a root plus an additional, non-morphemic string (e.g., &lt;em&gt;brothel&lt;/em&gt;, where &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not an English suffix). Current models of visual word processing assume the morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis, whereby decomposition obligatorily relies on &lt;em&gt;islands of regularity&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; namely, statistical orthographic regularities across letter strings, so that a string such as &lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt; is detected as a single morpho-orthographic unit, but &lt;em&gt;el&lt;/em&gt; is not (Rastle &amp;amp; Davis 2008). As such, decomposition is also argued to occur at early stages of word processing and &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; contact with the lexicon &amp;mdash; namely, before semantic information is accessed, so that decomposition occurs regardless of semantic transparency. This dissertation builds on these findings and primarily elicits the visual masked priming response to test the sensitivity of decomposition to any of the following higher-level linguistic properties (in addition to islands of regularities): phono-orthographic syllabification (along with whole-word lexicality, though indirectly), whole-word frequency, phonological conditioning, and syntactic selectional restrictions. By doing so, this dissertation additionally provides insights regarding the unfolding of linguistic properties during visual word processing. The results reported here suggest that decomposition is affected by whole-word lexicality and whole-word frequency. Given that these two properties are generally considered to be accessed at late stages of processing, these findings seem to be arguing against current models. A model of early visual decomposition is proposed that is able to account for these findings without necessarily challenging the  morpho-orthographic decomposition hypothesis. In this model, decomposition accesses whole-word lexicality and frequency through a multi-step mechanism that first generates multiple possible morpho-orthographic decomposition patterns of the visual stimulus and then evaluates them in parallel in order to choose the optimal candidate for activation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Allomorphy at Italian determiners at the morphology-phonology interface</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/italian-determiners/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/italian-determiners/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Allomorphic alternations are often accounted for by assuming them to be listed as idiosyncratic lexical entries. This paper analyzes the forms of the determiners (definite, indefinite, and demostratives) and definite prepositions across all Italo-Romance varieties, to show that such a view (for a review on accounts for the definite determiner, see Garrapa 2011) may lead to lose crucial generalizations at the morpho-phonological interface. Here, I propose a novel alternative account couched in the framework of &lt;em&gt;Distributed Morphology&lt;/em&gt; (Halle &amp;amp; Marantz1993), which makes use of morpho&amp;ndash;phonological operations, such as positive instructions (&lt;em&gt;rules&lt;/em&gt;), or &lt;em&gt;repairs&lt;/em&gt; triggered in response to violations of active &lt;em&gt;filters&lt;/em&gt; (Calabrese, 2009). I show that such an account is able to catch the underlying morpho&amp;ndash;phonological generalizations and therefore more coherently explain allomorphic phenomena occurring in the D&amp;ndash;domain.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The left periphery fragmented: Evidence from Italian</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/lp-fragmented/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/lp-fragmented/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;published in:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of NELS 48&lt;/em&gt;_ (edited by Sherry Hucklebridge and Max Nelson), 221-231. University of Iceland, Reykjavjk. CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform. 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cartography assumes that syntactic structures are more complex than the usual functional phrases; for example, CP is arguably made up of several projections, each of which is assigned specific scope-discourse features (such as focus and topic; Rizzi 1997). This paper contributes to the debate raging over whether all cartographic projections are always present. By looking at cross-clausal A-binding conditions in Italian, I show that an anaphor can be bound across clauses only when at the outmost phasal edge. This ultimately provides evidence that the full cartographic CP domain may not always be projected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greek Root Allomorphy without Spans</title>
      <link>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/spans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://robpetrosino.github.io/publication/spans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we focus on a set of data from Greek root-allomorphy that has been recently presented by Merchant (2015) as a counterexample to the strong hypothesis from Embick (2010) that linear adjacency between the trigger and the target is required for morphosyntactically-conditioned allomorphy to arise. We take issue with Merchant&amp;rsquo;s proposed alternative hypothesis which essentially eliminates adjacency as a locality condition for allomorphy, due to the fact that one such solution leads to the loss of a striking (and not language-specific) implicational generalization, namely, that root-allomorphy never occurs in the presence of overt verbalizers, a straightforward blocking effect under the linear adjacency hypothesis. We propose an alternative account of the problematic cases of Greek root-allomorphy, whereby ASP and VCE form a single node via post-syntactic re-bracketing, allowing us to save the linear adjacency hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
